we're continuing our discussion of
spinners in 3D from a mathematical point
of view in the last couple videos we've
been using Sigma matrices as basis
vectors in the XYZ directions
this might lead you to ask what the
sigma matrices actually are
should we view them as basis vectors
like little arrows in 3D space in the
XYZ directions or should we view them as
matrices
one answer to this question involves
Clifford algebras which I'll talk about
in a later video
in this video I'm going to try
explaining the relationship between
vectors and Paulie Spinners by showing
that the sigma matrices form a link
between ordinary 3D space and a pair of
two-dimensional spinner spaces
I'm going to show that the sigma
matrices actually have three indices one
vector index also called a tensor index
and a pair of spinner indices
the sigma matrices act as a link between
tensor indices and Spinner indices
allowing us to replace one tensor index
with a pair of spinner indices
this means that you can use the sigmas
to rewrite any tensor you've seen using
spinner indices which doubles the number
of indices
this is related to the concept of the
infeld van der Varden symbols although
the infeld van der Varden symbols are
only used for space-time and I will
cover them more fully in the next video
to help explain this we'll see that a
poly Vector can be written as the tensor
product of a spinner and a dual spinner
explaining all of this will require some
basic understanding of tensor Concepts
as a prerequisite like the tensor
product and dual vectors also called
co-vectors
I'll go over a quick review of these
Concepts in this video but I've included
links in the description to my tensors
for beginners series if you want a more
in-depth explanation
before we start I want to correct a
couple things from the previous video
when factoring a zero determinant Paulie
Vector I pulled this negative 1 outside
the square root and wrote it as I
this is a bit problematic because the
square root of negative one can be
either plus I or minus I this leads to
different sign conventions for the
results although this is expected since
we already know there are multiple
solutions for the spinner components
the most common convention in textbooks
is to leave the negative sign under the
square root
and get these formulas for the spinner
components
also in previous videos I've been saying
poly instead of Paulie I still say it
wrong in some parts of this video but
moving forward I'll try to use the
correct pronunciation
let's start by reviewing some basic
tensor Concepts
if I have a vector v living in
two-dimensional space I can write it as
a linear combination of basis vectors E1
and E2 using components V1 and V2
notice that I've written the indices on
V1 and V2 as upper indices these are not
exponents
one reason for this is that basis
vectors are often written in a row and
so the lower index tells us the position
in the row
and Vector components are often written
in a column and the upper indices tell
us their position in the column
another reason I've written the vector
components with upper indices is because
Vector components are contravariant
contravariant just means opposite change
meaning that Vector components change in
the opposite way that basis vectors do
for example if this vector's components
in this basis are 1 1 if I double the
length of the basis vectors by
multiplying them by 2 then I must have
the length of the components by
multiplying them by one half to get the
components one half one-half
the vector components changed in the
opposite way that the basis vectors did
the basis vectors grew and the vector
components shrunk
more generally if I change basis vectors
with a matrix then I must change the
vector components using the inverse
Matrix to balance the change out
I can also write this in summation
notation like this
some sources also choose to write these
summation formulas without including
summation symbols you can tell a
summation is happening whenever an upper
index letter is matched with a lower
index letter this is called Einstein
summation notation
next I'll introduce dual vectors which
go by many other names including
covectors and one forms
the bra vectors from quantum mechanics
are just another name for dual vectors
ordinary vectors are like arrows and are
good for representing objects with a
length and a direction such as velocity
dual vectors are like oriented stacks
and are good for representing objects
with a density and a direction such as a
traveling wave
larger dual vectors correspond to denser
stacks and smaller dual vectors
correspond to less dense stacks
a dual Vector is a machine that takes a
vector and outputs a scalar just by
counting the number of Stack sheets that
are pierced by the vector which is three
in this example
this idea of counting the number of
Stack sheets that a vector pierces gives
these two linearity laws for dual
vectors acting on vectors
the components of a dual Vector Alpha
are given by counting how many stack
sheets are pierced by the basis vectors
here the components of alpha are three
and two
as I said Vector components normally go
in columns with the upper index
indicating their position in the column
dual Vector components normally go in
rows with their lower index indicating
their position in the row
dual Vector components are written with
lower indices because they are covariant
this means they change in the same way
as basis vectors
let's say we have this dual Vector with
components two and four if we double the
length of the basis vectors then they
will pierce twice as many stack sheets
and so the Dual Vector components also
double two four and eight
we can also Define the Dual basis
written with epsilons
these are defined by this equation if
the Dual Vector index matches the vector
index we get one and if they don't match
we get zero
for example Epsilon 1 acting on E1 gives
one and the same for Epsilon 2 acting on
E2
and if the indices don't match we get
zero so Epsilon 1 acting on E2 gives
zero and same with Epsilon 2 acting on
E1
dual basis vectors are contravariant if
we double the length of the basis
vectors we must have the length of the
Dual vectors to make sure the equation
stays true
as I said Vector components normally go
in columns with the upper index
indicating their position in the column
dual basis vectors with their upper
indices also go in columns
when we have vectors living in a vector
space V we say that the Dual vectors
live in the corresponding dual Vector
space
this is often denoted by V Star in many
books but I'm just going to write the
Dual space as V dual
we can do row column multiplications to
get the scalar result of a co-vector
acting on a vector this is normally
called the inner product
but we can also do column row
multiplications to give us a two by two
Matrix which functions as a linear map
this is normally called the outer
product
this outer product array multiplication
can also be written abstractly with
symbols using this tensor product symbol
if we multiply this array product by a
scalar we can distribute the scalar to
either the column or the row
the tensor product also obeys this rule
where we can distribute the scalar
either to the left entry or to the right
entry
also if we have a column multiplied over
a sum of rows we can distribute over the
rows
similarly if we have a sum of columns
multiplied by a row we can distribute
the row over the columns
the tensor product follows similar rules
where if we have a sum on the right side
we can distribute over it the same goes
for Distributing over a sum on the left
side of the tensor product
some matrices like this one can be
written as the product of a single
column times a single row or in abstract
notation the tensor product of a single
vector and a single dual vector
however other matrices like this one
whose determinants are non-zero cannot
be written as a single column times a
single row
instead we break these apart into a sum
of matrices one for each component
bringing the scaling factors outside
each of these matrices now has a
determinant of zero
so we can Factor them into a column and
a row this shows that we can write any
Matrix as a sum of column row products
scaled by the appropriate coefficients
the same is true for tensor products any
linear map can be written as a linear
combination of tensor products of basis
vectors and basis dual vectors
all scaled by the appropriate
coefficients
I should also mention that in quantum
mechanics vectors are often written with
the KET notation and dual vectors are
often written with the bra notation
the inner product is then written as a
bra KET and the outer product is written
as a KET bra which can include or omit
the tensor product symbol depending on
the book
all of this reasoning that we've used
for vectors can also be used for
spinners
we have spinners which live in a spinner
space s and dual Spinners which live in
the Dual spinner space S Dual
I'm going to denote Spinners by bold
letters
let's say that we have a spinner PSI
that lives in s
a general spinner can be written as a
linear combination of basis Spinners
with lower indices and Spinner
components with upper indices
we can also write this in column row
notation like this or in summation
notation like this
similarly a dual spinner Zeta that lives
in as dual can be written as a linear
combination of dual basis Spinners with
upper indices and dual spinner
components with lower indices
again we can write this in column row
notation and summation notation
as you would expect basis Spinners are
covariant and Spinner components are
contravariant
dual spinner components are covariant
and dual basis Spinners are
contravariant
we can also do inner products of
spinners which gives a scalar and outer
products of spinners
so so far it doesn't seem like there's
much of a difference between vectors and
Spinners they both live in what is
formerly called a vector space they both
obey the same rules
the difference between them lies in
their relationship with each other
in the last video we learned that we can
take a powley vector with a determinant
of zero and write it as the product of a
column spinner and a row spinner and I'm
going to rewrite the components of the
row spinner using Zeta with lower
indices treating it as a dual spinner
on an abstract level what we're doing
here is writing a Pali Vector as the
tensor product of a spinner and a dual
spinner
more generally if a Paoli Vector has a
non-zero determinant we can break it up
into four matrices each with zero
determinant then write each of those as
a column spinner times a row spinner
more abstractly we write this as a sum
of tensor products between basis
Spinners and dual basis Spinners like
this
we can also write these outer products
in bra catch notation if we want
looking at the V components the upper
index specifies the position in the left
column or which Row in The Matrix
and the lower index specifies the
position in the right row or which
column of The Matrix
each of the sigma matrices can be
written this way as well
for example we can write Sigma X as a
linear combination of matrices broken
into column row products
more abstractly this is a linear
combination of tensor products of
spinners and dual spinners
the same can be done for Sigma y
and sigma Z
looking at these three formulas we have
12 coefficients that tell us how to sum
all these tensor products together
so now let's answer the question what
actually are the sigmas
well Sigma is actually a linear map from
the ordinary 3D Vector space V to the
four-dimensional space of spinner dual
spinner pairs which is s tensor S Dual
if we take our ex basis Vector from
ordinary 3D space and act on it with
Sigma we get a linear combination of the
four basis elements of the space s
tensor S Dual
the coefficients are 0 1 1 0 which are
exactly the entries of the Matrix Sigma
X
we can do the same thing with e y and
get the coefficients 0 plus I negative I
zero which are the entries of Sigma y
and with e z we get the coefficients 1 0
0 negative 1 which are the entries of
Sigma Z
we can label these 12 coefficients using
Sigma with three indices
to explain why these indices make sense
let's review an ordinary linear map L
from 3D space with one basis mapping to
another 3D space with another basis with
tilde's on top
if we act on E1 with L the output Vector
is some linear combination of the three
tilde basis vectors
the coefficients are written L with a 1
as the lower index because the input
Vector was the E1 basis Vector with a
lower index
the upper indices are written one two
three to match with the indices of the
three e tilde basis vectors
we can get similar sets of coefficients
for lov2 and lov3
notice that these raised indices of the
coefficients are opposite the lowered
indices for the basis vectors they are
associated with
this is because the upper coefficient
index and the lower basis Vector index
are summed together and so they must
have opposite elevations
now let's look at the linear map Sigma
acting on a basis Vector e x
the output is a linear combination of
the four spinner dual spinner products
each of the coefficients are written as
sigmas with a lower X index to match the
lower X index in the eex basis vector
we then require a pair of spinner
indices to tell us which basis element
the coefficients are associated with
labeled with 1 1 2 1 1 2 and 2 2.
note that the component indices are
written with opposite elevations
compared to the basis elements
for example the basis element with a
lower 2 and upper 1 is matched with a
coefficient with an upper 2 and a lower
one
we can do something similar for e y and
e z
and we can summarize all three of these
formulas using Einstein's summation
notation
so when we map a general 3D Vector small
v through the linear map Sigma we can
apply the linear map to each basis
Vector individually with the components
brought out in front
we get a linear combination in our
four-dimensional space of spinner dual
spinner products and these are the four
entries of the corresponding Paulie
Vector big V
we can also write this as an array
multiplication or as this summation
so the linear map Sigma forms a link
between our ordinary 3D Vector space V
and the 4D space of spinner dual spinner
products
when we wrote a 3D Vector small V in the
form of a poly Vector big V we were
really putting the small V Vector
through the linear map Sigma and writing
it in the space of spinner dual spinner
tensor products this is what allows us
to factor certain Paoli vectors into a
spinner and a dual spinner
note that all poly vectors can be
represented in our spinner pair space
but not every element of our spinner
pair space corresponds to a Pali vector
Pauli vectors must be traceless and
hermitian matrices
and our 4D spinner pair space can make
any general 2x2 matrix with complex
entries
also note that this map turns a single
Vector index into two spinner indices
so in some sense one vector index is
worth two spinner indices
we can apply this Sigma map to any
tensor T that we like and replace every
tensor index with a pair of spinner
indices
this is why Spinners can be thought of
as a tensor of rank one-half
a vector which is a rank 1 tensor is
equivalent to the product of a pair of
spinners each of rank one half
and a single Vector index requires two
spinner indices to be represented
and as seen in previous videos when
physical space is rotated by an angle
Theta the pair of spinners in the
corresponding spinner spaces each rotate
with half that angle Theta over two
the last thing I'll mention is that just
as it's possible to change basis in our
ordinary 3D Vector space V it's also
possible to change basis in our spinner
space s
for example we can double the length of
our S1 basis spinner
since dual basis Spinners are
contravariant the Dual basis spinner S1
must transform in the opposite way with
multiplication by one half
so our change of basis equations for
Spinners and dual Spinners are here and
we can rearrange these so that the tilde
basis is on the right side of the equal
sign
if we take a generic element of our
spinner pair space written in the
original basis we can change to the
tilde basis by applying these equations
one by one to each term in the sum
the 1 1 term gets a factor of one-half
and two that cancel
the 2-1 term gets a factor of two
the one two term gets a factor of
one-half
and the 2-2 term gets no additional
Factor
this gives the same object but written
in the tilde basis instead you can see
here that there are some extra numerical
factors in front of some components
we can also write the new components as
V tilde
so both of these formulas are just
different ways of writing the same
output from the sigma map
but because they are written in
different bases they give us different
components and they correspond to
different matrices
again the components in the new basis
can be written with v tilde
in this new spinner basis the components
of the sigma matrices would now contain
these factors meaning the sigma matrices
would now look like this
now we won't be changing spinner bases
very often in this video series but just
keep in mind it's something that can be
done and it will affect the components
of the sigma matrices
so to sum up this video just as vectors
live in Vector spaces and dual vectors
live in dual Vector spaces we have
spinners that live in spinner spaces and
dual Spinners that live in dual spinner
spaces spinner spaces obey all the rules
of linear algebra that would be expected
from Vector spaces but there is a
special linear map Sigma that Maps
vectors from 3D space into the space of
spinner dual spinner tensor products
this is where Paulie vectors and the
sigma matrices live
and it explains why we can Factor
certain Pali vectors into a spinner and
a dual spinner
the linear map Sigma has 12 coefficients
and it converts one tensor index into a
pair of spinner indices
in the next video when we cover Spinners
in four-dimensional space time the
equivalent Sigma map will be a 4x4
Matrix and its components are called the
infeld van der Varden symbols